<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE version PUBLIC  "-//harctoolbox.org//version//en" "version.dtd">
<!--
Copyright (C) 2011, 2012, 2013 Bengt Martensson.

This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or (at
your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
this program. If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses/.
-->
<version package = "org.harctoolbox.IrMaster"
       appName = "IrMaster"
       mainVersion = "0"
       subVersion = "3"
       subminorVersion = "3"
       versionSuffix = "pre"
       homepageUrl = "http://www.harctoolbox.org">

    <!-- Verbal description of the license of the current work. -->
    <licenseString>Copyright (C) 2011, 2012, 2013 Bengt Martensson.\n\n
This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.\n\n
This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for more details.\n\n
You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with this program. If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses/.</licenseString>

    <!-- Verbal description of licenses of third-party components. -->
    <thirdPartyString>
Makehex was written by John S. Fine (see LICENSE_makehex.txt), and has been translated to Java by Bengt Martensson.
ExchangeIR was written by Graham Dixon and published under GPL3 license. Its Analyze-function has been translated to Java by Bengt Martensson.
DecodeIR was originally written by John S. Fine, with later contributions from others. It is free software with undetermined license.
IrpMaster was created using ANTLR3, which is free software with BSD license.
IrMaster uses PtPlot for plotting IR sequences; this is free software with UC Berkeley Copyright.
Icons from the Crystal project are used; these are released under the LGPL license.
        </thirdPartyString>
</version>